[Music]
go a little bit further in the lion
stance this morning and I was reading
the instructions for it again I found it
three times in the sutras and you know
Maitreya
and also cater chase I think get up Jace
is the most beautiful explanation and
there's five parts and I thought you
might we I have to review where where
that what they call apart you know where
do the part start where does part one
start where this pipe one end okay so
you might want to make some notes this
is not on your homework it's just a few
teach it to somebody you should know
where it's part one stop okay so part is
part one by the way it's sing her vision
betta right like shaking roar of the
lion we call lions dance but singer say
see her vision beta
and the Russian word girl Thunder okay
like that right okay all right
when you go up through the eight levels
and then you go to level nine which is
level nine has these two parts right you
you do a Wheel of Life which means
dependent origination which means you go
to your past life and see where things
came from which means your present life
depends on the past life right that's
dependent dependence and then we're
gonna today we're gonna finish level one
we'll go back to the teacher and it
doesn't have to be the same teacher okay
I think it's good to to appreciate all
your teachers and you know you might use
your mom or great school teacher or
something like that okay so you come
back to your teacher and then we're
gonna compare our vision of the teacher
as someone who comes from our seeds or
past-life seeds compare it to our normal
perception of them as teachers irritated
today or a teacher is nice today or okay
like that and you don't think of where
that's coming from
you see what I mean so there's always a
correct perception involved in your
wrong perceptions okay
you are perceiving a teacher they do
exist
there is someone talking to you teaching
you and and that's not wrong that's a
correct perception we call pramana
correct perception but at the same time
with most of the time we have a feeling
about the teacher that they are deciding
what to say today they are thinking they
are planning the class they
the homework okay it's too long wait
till you see today's and you in your
heart you have a feeling that they
decided how long to make the homework
they wrote the questions they wrote this
one weird question that they didn't
cover in class and things like that that
feeling is what's wrong okay that
feeling is what's not real and teacher
the part of the teacher that that
feeling sees is not there and that's
emptiness okay so there's two
perceptions going on when you look at
the teacher right number one oh this is
the person who helped me when I was in
school and they taught me many great
things and I'm so grateful to them
that's correct
that that's a correct perception but
there's a feeling under it that oh this
person decided what to put on the
homework this person's making it too
long this person's getting covered is in
class that feeling that it's coming from
them is wrong and we always have both
feelings going on so obviously we're not
saying emptiness is that there's no
teacher there okay it's not true that
Buddhism says there's no teachers you
know and you shouldn't respect your
teacher or something like that okay it's
just that any problem you see with the
teacher is coming from you
just kidding any good things they're
also good okay it's okay so the homework
is coming from you don't blame me I'm
just a postman what's it mean postman
who wants to explain postman nobody's
too early Berta Berta from Mexico good
keep going yeah understand okay you
write a letter getting Michael writes a
letter to Geshe Michael say you are
stupid and then give it to the post
office and then three days later is
probably Mexico City in my in my town
it's three weeks later post 90 then the
postman comes back with my letter that I
have a letter for you
and I open it up and I get angry at the
postman okay so that they're not the
person who wrote the letter okay
everything that you experience including
homeworks you wrote the homework I'm
just the delivery man okay I'm just the
UPS guy alright and I'm just delivering
to you wisdom that you shared past life
okay so at level 9 of the lions dance
we're gonna go into dependent
origination which is where did this
teachers good quality come from looking
and it's tradition to focus on a good
quality you could focus on a bad quality
but then you just you just increase
those seeds you just strengthen those
seeds it's not that the teacher has no
bad college they have been calling but
it's like the bad qualities of your wife
or your husband if you focus on them
they will just grow
bigger and bigger so you know do what
you can to fix them but focus on
something sweet okay because life is
short and you know my life I was 25
yesterday then something happened and
when you hit 60 you get this wisdom yeah
I met my old lady the other day 94 I
asked her tell me what happens at 90 you
know and but at 60 you realize don't
waste your time with stupid people and
don't waste your time with stupid things
you know and you don't have time so just
focus on the cool things you know and
enjoy the cool things and just you see
some do you know the Tibetan saying do
tu cama new if you smell a fart don't go
like this oh who find it where I don't
don't smell a fart twice it's a Tibetan
sing just put your nose to the good side
you know and don't don't worry about you
don't have time so anyway we focus on
the good things of the Lama or a teacher
we go into the dependence of it which is
it could be past life it could be what
you did last week okay
that's dependent and then we're gonna
come back and imagine the teacher how we
met the teacher the first time you know
was it an accident and then I just
happen to be there and then we're gonna
pretend that we're gonna bring a new
teacher right who didn't come from us
we're gonna purposely try to imagine a
teacher who didn't come from us and
we're gonna look at them and think about
them and then we're gonna cancel them
and ask them to go away okay
that's what emptiness
emptiness in in in lions dancing
language that's called gopuram Jukes
agape
Namjoo cessation meditation it just
means cancel cancel meditation cancel
this teacher who didn't come from me
they don't exist
okay cancel it go ping Jung Joon okay
when we reach that we have finished the
first round of the five rounds of the
lion dance okay so we're gonna go for
that today all right and then we'll do
some other stuff for a while then I'll
take you back down if we have time
that's the second round okay you go from
you go back down from nine to eight
seven six five four where it is done
yeah it's traditional not to go back to
the air conditioner it's traditional to
stop and perform them at the heartbeat
okay
formula number one okay and that would
be the second round so that's the first
two rounds at the Lions dance I think
it's on your homework today I think
today in your retreat college you have
to do the two levels okay and you can do
it once you can do it twice all right
it's up to you this homework number two
probably won't have time to to do the
meditation too right huh I'm sorry I got
a little crazy three is even worse okay
I don't know about 4 yet okay all right
so please get ready to meditate turn off
your phone which you're not using anyway
blow your nose
it really helps okay
[Applause]
you're welcome to record if you want to
recording okay especially if you think
you might like to listen to it this
afternoon then you can follow it nice
music
okay let's go
bye bye John with you with you Ashley
okay lion stance let's try two rounds
okay so normally we would start with our
breath but we're gonna start we jump
straight into the air conditioner except
it's no air conditioner so how about
little noises in the room okay
little noises in the room
[Music]
personally I decide if I if it's a 10
birthday or a 20 birthday 10 birthday
means I'm late for work I try to do
about 10 breaths per level level and
then 20 breath day means I have time and
I can go slow so let's do a 20 breath
day since we're on retreat
rest your mind on the sound like you
rest your head on a pillow don't fight
don't struggle just have fun relax
Buddhists like people from other
religions tend to specialize in feeling
guilty and the deeper they go into
Buddhism the more guilty feelings they
have because it's impossible to do all
the things you're supposed to do so
today let's just try to have fun and
enjoy the meditation and we'll worry
about all the other things we're
supposed to do later on this is being
here sitting here is what you're
supposed to do right now enjoy life is
short
and then please come to your heartbeat
and then come in your heart inside
beautiful Sun filled sunlight filled
meditation room I like to put lots of
cushions on the floor it's quiet
you can feel the heart beating around
now we expand the space within the heart
and there are outer rooms around the
edge of the heart and we go into an
inner chamber into the center of the
heart deeper part of the heart the core
and the walls of the heart are still
beating but they're difficult to hear no
they sound far away the inner core of
the heart once we get inside is still a
very beautiful expansive space with lots
of sunlight
and inside that inner core of the heart
there's a small table next to you on the
table is a small sugar bowl and you dip
your finger in and it comes out with
some crystals on it sugar crystals and
you focus on one of those crystals and
you decide to put your mind inside the
crystal you kind of squeeze in one side
of the crystal but when you get inside
again there's even a more beautiful
meditation room meditation space lots of
light comfortable cushions beautiful
altar and you are meditating inside a
crystal inside the inner chamber of your
heart inside your heart inside your body
more quiet no heartbeat son
I'm done single-pointed place
we're going to show off our flexibility
mental flexibility so inside the sugar
crystal we will imagine huge ocean
infinite ocean deep blue deep water very
quiet stretching beyond the horizon
follow it with your mind deep and wide
infinite and show that you can go from a
very tight focus to a very broad focus
this is flexing your meditation muscle
still inside the crystal
first formless realm
now add the blue sky above the ocean
goes farther and farther no limit follow
the sky to the edges of the ocean as
high as you can
and stretch your meditation myself
either
infinite sky
you would be more quiet if we turn the
mind off completely so just as an
exercise in concentration and not
because it has anything to do with
emptiness we'll turn off the mind stop
thinking if thoughts come out feelings
pictures then face each one stop it and
come back to the silent mine which is
not thinking
a fourth formless realm level we will
keep the mind turned off no thinking
but if random thoughts come up then just
let them flow through the mind don't
confront them don't attach to them don't
engage with them just let them flow
through ignore them
go to a more quiet core of the mind
without thinking and ignore the outside
bubble surface level of thoughts
feelings
and now for the first time in this
meditation we bring a meditation object
which should be something meaningful
it's something important not like the
sky or the sea or the heartbeat it
should be something which has a heavy
karma which can make our mind more
elevated more beautiful and so we're
going to invite one of the teachers in
our life to come to this room sit in
front of us meditate with us so choose
one of the teachers in your life all of
us have many many teachers some of them
we don't think about or we don't
recognize them but even people who have
heard us in our life they're also
teaching us about ourselves and about
our reactions so bringing a teacher to
sit with you
now think of one beautiful collie of
this teacher something that helped you
even if it was painful and write a movie
about how you planted that quality that
you see after that we'll take a break
so just five minutes travel to another
country and to another time in history
imagine how you might have been and
enjoyed finding the time in place where
you planted the seeds to see your
teacher this way
and now please come back to your teacher
three long exhales at the end of each
exhale please the the lungs will pass
the breathing will pause and then push
out a little more air and this prevents
a buildup of tidal air or extra air in
your lungs and that helps prevent
nervousness or anxiety during meditation
so it's really long exhales when you
come to the end of the exhale push a
little bit more out that stomach will
tighten
and then slowly open your eyes take a
stretch
drink something okay
Joe you have a microphone ok any
questions about that part No
okay
hmm
when you choose a teacher it's easy to
go for a llama or somebody like that
I've had people in my life who were very
contentious and I chose to see them as
teachers my question is if you at what
point can you discern if I'm just giving
that negativity more and more juice by
bringing it into my thinking versus
honoring the role that I now perceive
them in okay so the question is if you
know kind of the mood today was maybe we
take as a teacher we visualize someone
who gave us trouble and maybe someone
who hurt us and then we tried to see how
they improved us and made us stronger
and the question was you know what if I
kind of start to focus on them what they
did to me and then the whole meditation
becomes that and it gets maybe it will
just make my seat stronger for thinking
about how they hurt me actually the same
thing happened to me during this
meditation so let's see what we should
do I think it takes some courage to use
a teacher in the meditation someone who
hurt you in the past and then I think it
takes a lot of strength or discipline to
try to focus on what what you learned
from and how you grew from that
experience
and I think if what happened to me
probably with the same I started to
wallow in how they hurt me and and it
kind of strengthened my negative seeds
about them that that my feelings that
they hurt me and I forgot to think very
much about how they improved me which
probably means they didn't improve me I
don't know but yeah I think it just
takes awareness and we cautious
initiation is a mental function that you
can learn to develop it's a smoke
detector in your mind and it's supposed
to go off BPP if you find your mind
going somewhere else so I think that's a
separate skill that we have to develop
and it's kind of a detector that the
mind is wandering or the - coin
someplace where it shouldn't be going
and it's a part of meditation muscle
that we don't were not born with it and
as a meditator you have to develop it
and you have to purposely develop it and
so in my house the other night I have
three fire alarms one by one they went
off for no reason just it's not
I changed the battery they still went on
Lok and so actually I just tore them out
of the ceiling and called the
electrician's and you put them back put
another on there
[Music]
and then not for the electrician to come
it was a couple days and then I was
thinking during this couple of days I'm
sort of worried that there if there's a
fire I'll just sleep through it and keep
sleeping for a long time and so it's
like that you have to install a new
piece of your mind that watches the rest
of your mind to make an alarm okay and
yeah that's all you can do if you keep
going on that train of thought you just
strengthen the negative scenes yeah so
I'll try to improve my smoke detector
also anybody else I guess I get the
bugger from Kichler
this is from this is from the livestream
so this isn't my question okay just
kidding it's actually obliged to elicit
blamin on you this is from Katie in
Colorado
Katie fetch you mean the mommy the
pregnant mommy soon-to-be mother yes
she asks in the 8 levels I have trouble
with the physical the physical body
versus the body in the meditating room
like I go back and forth between the
visualization and my body in real-time
any suggestions well if your body's
kicking that's a problem
wait six months yes sometimes the needs
of your body are stronger than your
meditation right your knees hurt or your
back hurts or you took you to see yoga
yesterday and everything hurts but yeah
there's a skill we shouldn't ignore our
body right if something hurts you should
check it out if you're like me if
something hurts inside I tend to just
wait a while and a couple of weeks and
see if something's going on or not and
and I think there's important if
something really feels strange inside
your body you should go to a doctor and
there's a kind of laziness where you're
like oh I I don't want to think about it
you know I feel shy to go to the doctor
and my doctor is like more difficult to
see than Trump but but then you you know
I think as you get older you you see
people die at strange moments and you're
like oh if something feels strange
inside my body and I should ask somebody
who knows about it and and I should do
something but then there are other parts
of your body cold pains and problems
with your knees or with your back and I
think as a meditator you have to learn
to ignore it you know you have to check
it out make sure it's not you know
something wrong with your heart or
something and
once the doctor said there's nothing
really there then you have to learn to
ignore your body so that's you know if
you meditate really seriously an hour a
day most of the time your legs will fall
asleep and there's pins and needles and
your legs for a while and just stay
there don't move okay if you move it'll
feel better for a while and it'll hurt
again if you don't move it'll hurt a lot
and then it'll go away and you don't
have to think about it and don't get up
quickly you will break your ankle okay
because your legs fell asleep so my
suggestion I mean if you're gonna
meditate seriously and you have some
kind of pains in your body you have to
just learn to ignore them and and work
through them it's a matter of willpower
it's not gonna get better as you get
older unless your karma is really
improving and yeah I think you have to
learn to be tough guy there's a place in
meditation to be a tough guy and you
just have to sit it down also if you've
had some kind of event in your life
someone criticized you yesterday or or
something happened
personal on a personal level someone did
something to your or something said
something to you that's like a physical
pain it will come up in your mind as
you're meditating and I think as a
meditator at some point you just have to
learn to be a tough guy
okay it's not gonna go away quickly you
can try to deal with the seeds but until
the new seeds take over you're gonna
have those pains physical and emotional
pains and I really think my own
experience
I've been meditating for 45 years
there's sometimes you just have to tough
it out and you have to say okay my legs
hurt I understand they're not gonna not
hurt okay let's go back to the
meditation okay you could break your
meditation but then your meditation
doesn't improve okay so I think at some
point you have to learn to ignore your
body okay because that pain is coming
from your sins you can change it and you
should work on changing it but there's
always a time gap between the new season
old sins so during that time gap which
is like while the husband is still
yelling okay but you know it's coming
from you and you just have to be a tough
guy you know smile and tough it out
I think you have to be tough to be a
meditator okay to be a serious meditator
you have to learn to ignore them pain
okay one more question and then we'll
take a break so before yes I quit the
question actually came from Alex Rowland
not Katie so funny inapplicable but I
don't think alex has anyone kicking
but if you do congratulations she's Alex
it's a girl by the way
nope okay another one I can grab huh
there's another question okay quick and
then these guys wanna pee pee they I was
informed yesterday that I keep
announcing a pee-pee break and delaying
and it's really cruel so this is a
question from Taiwan the person's name
is singing Lin the question is sorry
when you mention about the blue sky
above I feel like I'm outside of the
earth in the cosmos have I gone too far
and need a pull back yeah I used to
teach it go all the way to the end of
the universe and nowadays I'm kind of
trying to match the the sea with this
guy two different kinds of blue but if
you go past the blue into outer space
and keep going that's even better okay
the name of that level is Nam Katya
which means endless space Nam satire
which means endless consciousness and
yeah that's even better if you can do it
that's even better
yeah that's fine okay let's take a
little break okay 10-15 minutes and then
we'll come back and we'll go back down
just so I can say I did numbered level
winning on round number two with you
okay all right we start to do the
emptiness part
okay so we we finish the meditation
about our teachers quality we traced it
back to our past life and now we're
going to go into a cessation meditation
which means we're going to focus on how
that's not not coming from me okay
and that's emptiness the original
Maitreya instructions are tension to
look toned down look meeting the top
agenda looked undone means how did I get
in trouble meditate on that or how did
this beautiful thing come to me meditate
on that
that's called look tune then look me
turn look me turn means then go the
other way back out and cancel a teacher
who's not coming from you okay so really
the second part of dependence is the
emptiness you see so here we go
sometimes they look meter nowadays it's
called Languedoc which means same thing
reversed the feeling that this teacher
is not coming from you okay that the
homework is not coming from you okay
here we go
ready and we won't spend long on it
so this time let's start with a breath
counting breath since we're doing deeper
retreat this week it's possible you will
start to get loan long this sort of a
honor to get them it means you're
meditating you're trying to meditate and
it low means the excess of prana in your
body and you start to feel nervous or
anxiety you have trouble sleeping and a
very nice way to prevent it is this
trick of when you exhale during your
meditation push out some more air after
the muscles tighten at the end of the
exhale then exhale a little bit more not
like don't go crazy with it but just
comfortably exhale a little more and
then extra prana extra breath which are
related won't build up in your body so
here we go let's take ten breaths
counting exhale first inhale second and
on the exhale you'll be careful to after
the natural pause of the lungs push out
a little bit more
keep a relaxed face don't get all
serious enjoy meditation you're on
vacation here that diamond mountain have
some fun
then place bring your teacher to mind
again bring them in front of you to
meditate together
then I like to think of how I first met
my teacher there's the normal well
there's the history of it which was I
was in a certain place and they came to
that place and we met each other and
that perception is correct that's how it
happened and there's nothing wrong with
that but there's a second perception
that always goes along with the first
one which says that that meeting was by
accident I was in a certain place they
happen to come to that place at that
same hour and then we met each other and
that part of the perception of my
teacher is mistaken there are no
accidents in life because that teacher
coming into my house appearing at the
door is actually coming from me from my
sins so they're coming to my house is
coming from me and when they left my
house that day those seats were wearing
out and they left the house so during
this next meditation which is stopping
meditation and we're starting round two
of the lion stance try to remember how
you met this teacher and tried to
acknowledge that the first perception is
correct you did meet them they did come
to your house they did leave your house
that part is correct
but try to get in touch with this other
feeling that it all happened by accident
it was coming from their side and try to
cancel that feeling trying to stop that
feeling and recognize that they're
coming and they're going what's coming
from your seeds okay here we go
now we'll come down back down the eight
levels which will complete the second
round so come back drop the meditation
object and come back to stopping the
mind very very quiet and not worrying
about extra thoughts lead them on the
outside
I usually spend half the time coming
down then I spent coming up level seven
we're coming out from the center of the
mind mind is still turned off but we are
fighting to stop random thoughts and
that creates a little noise in the mind
back to the infinite sky
back to the ocean
back to the sugar crystal
and back to the inner core at the heart
lots of sunlight
back inside the heart with the walls
beating lots of sunlight
back to watching your heart from your
body
and three large access
and slowly open your eyes take a stretch
drink something
okay someone's fun you might want to
turn it off okay yeah okay
all right then any last questions about
the meditation no oh here we go
Thank You Kesha may I ask top when we go
up we are expanding from the sky the
ocean but when we are backing down
do we still expanding always still
picture or we track yeah good question q
as we go up we expand the sky and as we
come down yeah we retract to the middle
and that's a tradition for meditation in
the diamond way in the taunting classes
so it's a important to get this feeling
of things coming back to the center it's
a good question yes Luca had a question
Thank You Sheila I have a question
during this time my sensation meditation
because this time I choose the quality
of my teacher is a kind of tolerance of
10 so during the cessation meditation I
started to think about his tolerance of
pay is from me but also the pain is also
from me so I feel quite a suffering
inside of me I started to feel kind of
guilty why I shouldn't make so much pain
okay my teacher yeah that's a good
question
when you reach enlightenment you get
four bodies one of the bodies is called
headquarters body
it's an emitter bath in paradise and
it's definition is Nippon London which
means five fixed qualities and one of
those qualities is that all around you
you only see high body suffers around
those body suffers are not other people
there are the people in this movement
you see so when you get enlightened you
will see everybody in this room as a
high Bodhisattva how they see themselves
it is different you know because of the
dog and the chew toy and the pen so how
they experience their own life you don't
have to take blame for that or take
credit for that
you see that's there the seeds so you
will experience them as
my body suffer how they experience
themselves is maybe completely different
they may think I'm suffering you see so
it's not your fault how they feel about
themselves you see that mean even after
you become Buddha the people around you
may feel that there are normal people
you will see them as a high-level
Bodhisattva you can't stop it you can't
help it that's Buddhahood so you don't
have to feel responsible for for how
they they see themselves that's that's
not that's their seat
okay like that all right so when you're
not a Buddha maybe you see people around
you have some pain but maybe they see
themselves as Buddha you see so yeah you
can think the reason I see pain is
coming from me I have to improve but
don't worry about how they feel could be
they see themselves as a Buddha okay
which one is correct we're gonna talk
about it today all right anybody else
let's go let's go through the class